So why do we learn mathematics?
لماذا نتعلم الرياضيات؟
Essentially, for three reasons:
لثلاثة أسباب رئيسية:
calculation,
الحساب،
application,
التطبيق،
and last, and unfortunately least
وأخيرا، وللأسف، السبب الأقل أهمية
in terms of the time we give it,
وفقا لما نعطيه له من وقت،
inspiration.
هو الإلهام.
Mathematics is the science of patterns,
الرياضيات هى علم الأنماط،
and we study it to learn how to think logically,
و نقوم بدراستها لنتعلم أن نفكر بطريقة منطقية،
critically and creatively,
بتحليل و ابداع،
but too much of the mathematics that we learn in school
ولكن الكثير من الرياضيات التي نتعلمها في المدرسة
is not effectively motivated,
ليست محفزة على ذلك بشكل كاف،
and when our students ask,
وعندما يطرح طلبتنا سؤالهم،
"Why are we learning this?"
"لماذا ندرس هذه الأشياء؟"
then they often hear that they'll need it
غالبا ما يسمعون ردا بأنهم سيحتاجونها
in an upcoming math class or on a future test.
في حصة رياضيات قادمة أو في اختبار ما في المستقبل
But wouldn't it be great
ولكن، ألن يكون عظيما
if every once in a while we did mathematics
أن نقوم بحل بعض المسائل الرياضية كل فترة
simply because it was fun or beautiful
لأنها وببساطة ممتعة وجميلة، أو
or because it excited the mind?
لأنها تنشط العقل؟
Now, I know many people have not
الآن، أنا أعلم أن الكثيرين لم تكن لديهم
had the opportunity to see how this can happen,
الفرصة ليروا كيف من الممكن أن تصبح الرياضيات هكذا،
so let me give you a quick example
لذلك، دعني أوضح لك ذلك بمثال
with my favorite collection of numbers,
بمجموعتي المفضلة من الأرقام،
the Fibonacci numbers. (Applause)
أرقام فيبوناتشي. (تصفيق)
Yeah! I already have Fibonacci fans here.
مرحى! لدي هنا معجبين بـ فيبوناتشي بالفعل.
That's great.
هذا عظيم.
Now these numbers can be appreciated
الآن هذه الأرقام من الممكن النظر إليها
in many different ways.
بطرق مختلفة وعديدة.
From the standpoint of calculation,
من وجهة نظر الحساب،
they're as easy to understand
فأرقام فيبوناتشي سهلة الفهم كـ
as one plus one, which is two.
واحد زائد واحد يساوي اثنان.
Then one plus two is three,
ثم واحد زائد اثنان يساوي ثلاثة،
two plus three is five, three plus five is eight,
و ثلاثة زائد خمسة يساوي ثمانية،
and so on.
و هكذا.
Indeed, the person we call Fibonacci
بالتأكيد، الشخص الذي نسميه فيبوناتشي
was actually named Leonardo of Pisa,
كان في الواقع يسمى ليوناردو اوف بيزا،
and these numbers appear in his book "Liber Abaci,"
وتلك الأرقام ظهرت في كتابه "ليبر أباتشي،"
which taught the Western world
والتي علمت العالم الغربي
the methods of arithmetic that we use today.
الطرق الحسابية التي نستخدمها اليوم.
In terms of applications,
بالنسبة للتطبيق،
Fibonacci numbers appear in nature
أرقام فيبوناتشي تظهر في الطبيعة
surprisingly often.
بشكل متكرر مثير الدهشة.
The number of petals on a flower
عدد البتلات لزهرة
is typically a Fibonacci number,
ينطبق بشكل نموذجي على أرقام فيبوناتشي،
or the number of spirals on a sunflower
عدد لولبيات لزهرة الشمس
or a pineapple
أو الأناناس
tends to be a Fibonacci number as well.
تميل للتوافق مع أرقام فيبوناتشي ايضا.
In fact, there are many more applications of Fibonacci numbers,
في الواقع، هناك العديد من التطبيقات لأرقام فيبوناتشي،
but what I find most inspirational about them
ولكن الأكثر إلهاما الذي وجدته
are the beautiful number patterns they display.
هو الأنماط الجميلة للأرقام التي تتجلى بها.
Let me show you one of my favorites.
دعني أريك واحدا من أكثر ما أفضله.
Suppose you like to square numbers,
فلنفترض أنك تحب أن تربع الأرقام،
and frankly, who doesn't? (Laughter)
وبصراحة، من الذي لا يحب هذا؟ (ضحك)
Let's look at the squares
دعنا نلقى نظرة على تربيعات
of the first few Fibonacci numbers.
الأرقام الأولى لـ فيبوناتشي.
So one squared is one,
فتربيع واحد هو واحد،
two squared is four, three squared is nine,
مربع اثنان: أربعة، ومربع ثلاثة: تسعة،
five squared is 25, and so on.
ومربع خمسة: 25، وهكذا.
Now, it's no surprise
الآن، لا توجد مفاجئة
that when you add consecutive Fibonacci numbers,
أنه عند جمع رقمين متتابعين لأرقام فيبوناتشي،
you get the next Fibonacci number. Right?
تحصل على الرقم التالي لـ فيبوناتشي، أليس كذلك؟
That's how they're created.
فهكذا وُجدت.
But you wouldn't expect anything special
ولكنك لن تتوقع أي شيء مميز
to happen when you add the squares together.
أن يحدث بجمع تربيعات الأرقام معا.
But check this out.
ولكن، فلتجرب هذا.
One plus one gives us two,
واحد زائد واحد يساوي اثنان،
and one plus four gives us five.
وواحد زائد أربعة يعطينا خمسة.
And four plus nine is 13,
و أربعة زائد تسعة يساوي 13،
nine plus 25 is 34,
و تسعة زائد 25 يساوي 34،
and yes, the pattern continues.
و نعم، النمط يستمر في التتابع.
In fact, here's another one.
في الواقع، هاك نمط آخر.
Suppose you wanted to look at
افرض أنك أردت النظر إلى
adding the squares of the first few Fibonacci numbers.
جمع مربعات أرقام فيبوناتشي القليلة الأولى.
Let's see what we get there.
دعنا نرى ماذا سيقودنا هذا.
So one plus one plus four is six.
إذن، واحد زائد واحد زائد أربعة يساوي ستة.
Add nine to that, we get 15.
بإضافة تسعة، يصبح لدينا 15.
Add 25, we get 40.
أضف 25، نحصل على 40.
Add 64, we get 104.
أضف 64، يصبح لدينا 104،
Now look at those numbers.
الآن، انظر لهذه الأرقام.
Those are not Fibonacci numbers,
هذه ليست أرقام فيبوناتشي،
but if you look at them closely,
ولكن إذا أمعنت النظر،
you'll see the Fibonacci numbers
ستجد أن أرقام فيبوناتشي
buried inside of them.
قابعة هناك.
Do you see it? I'll show it to you.
هل تراهم؟ سأوضحهم لك.
Six is two times three, 15 is three times five,
ستة هي حاصل ضرب 2x3، و15 حاصل ضرب 3x5،
40 is five times eight,
40 اصل ضرب 5x8،
two, three, five, eight, who do we appreciate?
اثنان، ثلاثة، خمسة، ثمانية، لمن يعود الفضل؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Fibonacci! Of course.
فيبوناتشي! بالطبع.
Now, as much fun as it is to discover these patterns,
الآن، والذي بنفس القدر من المتعة هو أن نكتشف تلك الأنماط،
it's even more satisfying to understand
إنه غاية في الرضا أن نفهم
why they are true.
لماذا هى صحيحة.
Let's look at that last equation.
دعنا نجد اجابة على هذا السؤال الأخير.
Why should the squares of one, one, two, three, five and eight
لماذا يجب أن أن تكون تربيعات الأرقام واحد، وواحد، و اثنان، وخمسة، وثمانية
add up to eight times 13?
تساوي حاصل ضرب 8x13؟
I'll show you by drawing a simple picture.
سأوضح لك برسم صورة بسيطة.
We'll start with a one-by-one square
سنبدأ بمربع يمثل 1x1
and next to that put another one-by-one square.
والمربع التالي سيكون ايضا لـ 1x1.
Together, they form a one-by-two rectangle.
معا، يمثلان مستطيلا 1x2.
Beneath that, I'll put a two-by-two square,
تحته، سأضع مربعا 2x2،
and next to that, a three-by-three square,
وبجانبه، مربعا 3x3،
beneath that, a five-by-five square,
أسفل منه، مربعا 5x5،
and then an eight-by-eight square,
ثم مربعا 8x8
creating one giant rectangle, right?
مكوناً بذلك مستطيلا عملاقا، صحيح؟
Now let me ask you a simple question:
الآن دعني أسألك سؤالا بسيطا:
what is the area of the rectangle?
ما مساحة المستطيل؟
Well, on the one hand,
حسنا، من جانب،
it's the sum of the areas
انها مجموع مساحات
of the squares inside it, right?
المربعات بداخله، أليس كذلك؟
Just as we created it.
تماما كما صنعناه،
It's one squared plus one squared
انه مجموع مربع واحد في واحد
plus two squared plus three squared
زائد مجموع مربع اثنان وثلاثة
plus five squared plus eight squared. Right?
زائد مربع خمسة زائد مربع ثمانية، صحيح؟
That's the area.
فتكون هذه هي المساحة.
On the other hand, because it's a rectangle,
على الجانب الآخر، ولأنه مستطيل،
the area is equal to its height times its base,
فمساحته هى حاصل ضرب القاعدة في الإرتفاع،
and the height is clearly eight,
والارتفاع من الواضح أنه ثمانية،
and the base is five plus eight,
والقاعدة تكون خمسة زائد ثمانية،
which is the next Fibonacci number, 13. Right?
والذي مجموعهما هو رقم فيبوناتشي التالي، 13، أليس كذلك؟
So the area is also eight times 13.
فالمساحة ايضا هى حاصل ضرب ثمانية في 13،
Since we've correctly calculated the area
وبما اننا حسبنا المساحة بشكل صحيح
two different ways,
بطريقتين مختلفتين،
they have to be the same number,
فلابد أن يعطيا نفس الرقم،
and that's why the squares of one, one, two, three, five and eight
ولهذا السبب مربعات واحد، وواحد، واثنين، وثلاثة، وخمسة، ثمانية
add up to eight times 13.
تساوي حاصل ضرب ثمانية في 13.
Now, if we continue this process,
الآن اذا تابعنا هذه العملية،
we'll generate rectangles of the form 13 by 21,
سيتولد مستطيلات من حاصل ضرب 13 في 21،
21 by 34, and so on.
و21 في 34 وهكذا.
Now check this out.
الآن فلتجرب هذه.
If you divide 13 by eight,
لو قسمت 13 على ثمانية،
you get 1.625.
ستحصل على 1,625.
And if you divide the larger number by the smaller number,
ولو قسمت أكبر رقم بأصغرهم،
then these ratios get closer and closer
ستتقارب تلك النسب أكثر فأكثر
to about 1.618,
لحوالي 1.618،
known to many people as the Golden Ratio,
والتي معروفة لدى العديد بالنسبة الذهبية،
a number which has fascinated mathematicians,
الرقم الذي سلب لب الرياضيون،
scientists and artists for centuries.
والعلماء والفنانون ولعقود.
Now, I show all this to you because,
الآن، أنا أريك كل هذا لأن،
like so much of mathematics,
مثل أمورا كثيرة جدا في الرياضيات،
there's a beautiful side to it
هناك جانب جميل لها
that I fear does not get enough attention
والذي أخشى أنه لا يحظى بالإنتباه الكافي
in our schools.
في مدارسنا.
We spend lots of time learning about calculation,
نحن نقضي أوقاتا كبيرة نتعلم كيفية اجراء العمليات الحسابية،
but let's not forget about application,
ولكن دعنا لا ننسى أمر التطبيق،
including, perhaps, the most important application of all,
والذي يتضمن أكثر التطبيقات أهمية،
learning how to think.
وهو أن نتعلم كيف نفكر.
If I could summarize this in one sentence,
ولو يمكنني تلخيص ذلك في عبارة واحدة،
it would be this:
ستكون:
Mathematics is not just solving for x,
الرياضيات ليست فقط إيجاد حلا لمشكلة س ،
it's also figuring out why.
إنها ايضا معرفة السبب وراء الحل.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)